Puerto Rican Oral History Project records 1976.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Arroyo, Angel, 1973 August 9; 1976.001.004
  In the interview, Ángel Arroyo looks back on his professional life - including twenty years as a journalist - reviewing events he helped to publicize for the mid-twentieth century's Hispanic population of New York City. He recalls his early work experience in factories and in the import-exporting business. While the interview's primary focus is autobiographical, there is significant attention paid to socioeconomic and political concerns of the Puerto Rican community, as well as Spanish-language media in the city. His career as a professional writer and poet is one that stands in contrast with that of many other migrants who, due to financial and familial obligations, were often unable to pursue a formal education. Interview conducted by Ms. Ruiz and Ms. Torres.
  Arroyo, Angel M., 1912-; El Diario de Nueva York.; La Prensa Newspaper, Inc..; Puerto Rican Writers Association.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Education; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Puerto Rican poetry; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |v Newspapers; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Intellectual life; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Arroyo, Carmen Rosado, 1975 January; 1976.001.005
  Carmen Rosado Arroyo was born in the 1910s in the neighborhood of Melillas in Santurce, Puerto Rico. She moved to New York in 1923, where she had six children and spent most of her life as a housewife. She was involved in civic and religious activities and was a member of the First Spanish Presbyterian Church in Williamsburg. At the time of the interview in 1973, she was sixty-five years old and had been living in New York for approximately fifty-two years.
  In this interview, Carmen Rosado Arroyo briefly describes her life in Santurce, Puerto Rico and her first experiences in New York. Mrs. Rosado Arroyo talks about the beginnings of the First Spanish Presbyterian Church and the reasons for its establishment. She compares New York--as well as its population--of 1973, to the New York she knew during her first years in the city. She goes into detail as to how immigrants worked and lived together regardless of country of origin. Mrs. Rosado Arroyo discusses several social relief programs such as the Works Progress Administration, Civilian Conservation Corps, and welfare. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Civilian Conservation Corps (U.S.).; New York (N.Y.). Department of Public Welfare.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.. Presbytery of Brooklyn-Nassau.; United States. Works Projects Administration (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Race relations |z United States; Santurce (San Juan, P.R.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Bermudez, Justina, 1974 November 18; 1976.001.006
  Justina Bermúdez was born in 1921 in Puerto Rico. She arrived in Brooklyn in 1932 at the age of eleven. She first lived in the apartment of her seamstress aunt Rafaela Simmons; an address on Bedford Avenue, on the border of the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Bedford-Stuyvesant and Williamsburg. After Bermúdez briefly attended school while in her Aunt's care, she later moved to Hooper Avenue in Williamsburg and still resided there in 1974. Following her completion of the seventh grade, Bermúdez labored in factories, eventually working as a heat sealing operator (or lining specialist) in both a luggage and a leather handbag factory. At the time of the 1974 interview, she was retired. Justina Bermúdez died in April, 1983.
  In the interview, Justina Bermudez recalls growing up in Brooklyn after arriving from Puerto Rico at the age of eleven. She recalls the locations of various factories - where she initially worked with smoked fish - and eventually in a luggage factory, as well as a handbag factory as a heat sealing operator (or lining specialist). Bermudez touches on the social and recreational aspects of the Puerto Rican community; including someone she describes as one of the first Puerto Ricans in New York radio, Santiago Grevi, by name. References are also made to several nightclubs frequented by members of the community. Also, she describes the ethnic makeup of the Bedford and Flushing Avenues area, which lies on the border between the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Bedford-Stuyvesant and Williamsburg. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Bermudez, Justina, 1921-; Grevi, Santiago; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Bonilla, Carmelita, 1973 May 12; 1976.001.007
  Sister Carmelita Bonilla was born in Cabo Rojo, Puerto Rico in 1908. She journeyed to Brooklyn in 1923, becoming the first Puerto Rican Roman Catholic nun in New York City. During the height of the Great Depression of the 1930s, Bonilla ran a community center on Gold Street in the Vinegar Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn; organizing clubs and activities for impoverished residents - many from European immigrant backgrounds - and providing vital social services, both for existing ethnic enclaves as well as the fledgling Puerto Rican community. She was stationed at Saint Peter's Church at 117 Warren Street in Brooklyn's Columbia Waterfront District, where she offered religious instruction to parishioners, including many new arrivals from Puerto Rico. In 1967 she was assigned to St. Joseph’s Roman Catholic Church on Pacific Street in the Prospect Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. By that time, she had completed a bachelor's degree from the University of Puerto Rico at Río Piedras, and a master's degree from Santa María in Ponce. In 1991 she moved into the motherhouse of the Blessed Trinity Mother Missionary Cenacle in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. She remained a member of the Missionary Servants of the Most Blessed Trinity until her death in 2003.
  In the interview, Sister Carmelita Bonilla describes conditions for the residents of Brooklyn's waterfront during the 1920s and 1930s. The interview pays particular attention to the various personalities - including police, politicians and gangsters - she had to deal with in order to accomplish her social and religious work with the Catholic community at large, with the narration focusing on Bonilla's work with newly arrived migrants from her native Puerto Rico. She discusses neighborhood life and some local institutions, such as the Cumberland Hospital, and their relationship with the community. Bonilla also recalls details from her initial training and decision to join a religious order, her education, as well as her personal role in helping the poor and needy, particularly among New York's Puerto Ricans. Interview conducted by Pedro Rivera and Tomas Rivera.
  Bonilla, Carmelita, 1908-; Kelly, James; Tapia, Carlos; Weber, Louis; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Columbia Heights (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); DUMBO Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Navy-yards and naval stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Rican women |x Political activity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Vinegar Hill (New York, N.Y.)
- Carrasquillo, Magdalena, 1974 November 15; 1976.001.008
  Magdalena Acosta Carrasquillo was born in Ponce, Puerto Rico in 1910. After immigrating to New York in July 1921, she became a resident of Brooklyn. Carrasquillo had a tenth grade-level education, worked at a factory and as a housewife, and was an active member of various social clubs and religious organizations. She married the community advocate Rosendo Acosta and with him she raised four children, and for twelve years prior to 1974, a grandson.
  In this first of two interviews, Magdalena Acosta Carrasquillo reflects on her association with the social, political, and civic organizations that defined the Puerto Rican community in Brooklyn at the time of her arrival in the 1920s and into the 1930s. She notes specific individuals; Carlos Tapia, Luis Hernández and Antonia Denis, and places of significance for Puerto Ricans like the Betances Democratic Club and the Downtown neighborhood of Brooklyn. She also refers to her personal job-hunting process in the years 1925 to 1940. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Carrasquillo, Magdalena, 1910-; Denis, Antonia; Tapia, Carlos; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Factories |z New York (State); Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Carrasquillo, Magdalena, 1974 December; 1976.001.009
  In this second of two interviews, Magdalena Acosta Carrasquillo reflects on her association with the social, political, and civic organizations that defined the Puerto Rican community in Brooklyn at the time of her arrival in the 1920s and into the 1930s. She notes specific individuals; Carlos Tapia and Antonia Denis, and places of significance for Puerto Ricans who experienced discrimination. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Carrasquillo, Magdalena, 1910-; Denis, Antonia; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Factories |z New York (State); Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico
- Carrero, Jean, 1974 November 2; 1976.001.010
  Jean Carrero was born in Las Marías, Puerto Rico in 1914 and migrated to Brooklyn, New York in 1926 with her parents. She studied bookkeeping at The Girls’ Commercial High in the Prospect Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn but decided to abandon her studies as professional work was difficult to come by during the Great Depression. Carrero was married to Cecilio Rivera and was a homemaker during most of her life before working in New York City's Mental Health Department. Carrero was a member of the civic group Las Hijas de María.
  In the interview, Jean Carrero speaks about her first impressions of Brooklyn, New York and the challenges she faced when migrating from Puerto Rico, especially those relating to getting an education in English. She narrates several incidents regarding racial tensions between Italians and Puerto Ricans in the workplace and in Spanish Harlem. She also describes working conditions during the Great Depression and discrimination towards Puerto Ricans in the workplace. She talks about several Puerto Rican clubs such as the Casino Puertorriqueño and Las Hijas de María. She goes into detail about the role of the woman in a marriage and discusses the disparities between being a married woman and being a married man. She concludes the interview by speaking about the challenges that newer generations of Puerto Ricans face in the 1970s and her hopes for the future of the Puerto Rican community. Carrero’s husband is in the background being interviewed as well. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Carrero, Jean, 1914-; New York (N.Y.). Department of Public Welfare.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican families |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Language; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z United States
- Colon, Ramon, 1973 April 30; 1976.001.011
  Born in 1902, Ramón Colón was a migrant from Cayey, Puerto Rico who came to New York in 1918. Educated at Brooklyn College, he worked for New York State's Division of Human Rights, as well as in the insurance and real estate industries. He was a long-time leader of the Republican Party of Kings County.
  In this interview, Ramón Colón contributes a wealth of information about the community benefactor Carlos Tapia, and discusses a variety of related themes: from the naming of a public school, to his perception of the younger generation of Puerto Ricans living in Brooklyn. He also discusses other civic leaders and issues pertaining to the Puerto Rican community - as well as biographical details from his own life - at length. Interview conducted by Pedro Rivera, Tomas Rivera and Elba Correa.
  Colon, Ramon, 1902-; New York (State). Division of Human Rights.; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |v Newspapers; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Cortes, Esther Mercado, 1973 August 6; 1976.001.012
  Born in Puerto Rico circa 1910, Esther Mercado Cortés migrated to Brooklyn in 1934. She spent most of her years as a housewife, a caregiver to a sick husband, and a mother to three children. One of her children is Dr. Sonia Nieto, a leading bilingual educator and author.
  In the interview, Esther Mercado Cortés recounts her efforts to find employment in Brooklyn factories after arriving in America alone. She also speaks of the poor housing conditions in the Borough Hall section in the neighborhood of Downtown Brooklyn during the late 1930s. Interview in Spanish conducted by Ms. Torres with an introduction by Jaime Barreto.
  Cortes, Esther M., 1910-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ponce (P.R.); Puerto Rican families |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- de Jesus, Pastor, 1974 October 25; 1976.001.013
  Pastor de Jesús was born on a small family farm in Rio Piedras, Puerto Rico in 1889. A veteran of World War I, he arrived in Brooklyn on April 1, 1920 to visit relatives, and has resided here ever since. First inhabiting an apartment on Sands Street in what is now the DUMBO neighborhood of Brooklyn, he eventually settled on Pennsylvania Avenue in the neighborhood of East New York, where he lived in 1974. A retired furniture factory worker at the time of the 1974 interview, de Jesús served as one of the founders of American Legion Post # 1105.
  In the interview, Pastor de Jesús reveals his dichotomous role as a native-born Puerto Rican and American veteran of the First World War. He describes the ethnic demographics and everyday life in Brooklyn since his arrival in 1920, with a focus on his community activism. He also mentions some of the prominent names of New York City's Puerto Rican community during his lifetime. de Jesús describes working in a furniture factory in the early and mid-twentieth century, including one that manufactured wooden refrigerators. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  de Jesus, Pastor, 1889-; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); DUMBO Historic District (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Diaz, Mercedes, 1974 April 11; 1976.001.014
  Born circa 1926, Mercedes Díaz left Santurce, Puerto Rico with family in 1931. First living on Manhattan Avenue in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, she later moved to the Bronx in 1941. A high school graduate, Díaz went on to be a mail clerk.
  In the interview, Mercedes Díaz comments on the housing and social conditions of the Puerto Rican community in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn and Brooklyn in general. She relates the issues of ethnicity that factored into life among neighbors from the Jewish and Italian population. Interview conducted by Bob Rosado.
  Access is available onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Use of oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires permission from BHS by contacting library@brooklynhistory.org.
  Diaz, Mercedes; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Donnes, Cesar, 1974 November 23; 1976.001.015
  César Donnes was born in 1904 in Puerto Rico and was raised on a farm until his adulthood. He arrived in Brooklyn in 1928. For the next thirty years, Donnes worked in a factory. In 1974, Donnes was retired, a widower, and a forty-six year resident of Brooklyn.
  In the interview, César Donnes recounts his early employment experience; farming in Puerto Rico and factory work in Brooklyn. He describes the Downtown neighborhood of Brooklyn; in particular Sands, Gold and Adams Streets. Donnes relates the origins and formations of the Aqueybana Democratic Club, Puerto Rican Civic Union and other early Puerto Rican organizations in Brooklyn. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Donnes, Cesar, 1904-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Factories |z New York (State); Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Estepa, Julio, 1974 December 7; 1976.001.016
  Born in Puerto Rico in 1918, Julio Estepa came to Brooklyn in 1928. He lived in Brooklyn from 1928 to 1934 and returned to Puerto Rico until 1946, when he came back to Brooklyn permanently. Estepa worked for the federal government as a security specialist. Julio Estepa died in November, 2005.
  In the interview, Julio Estepa talks about the circumstances surrounding life in Puerto Rico and in New York City at various points in his life. He describes what community support existed in Brooklyn for Puerto Ricans and which individuals helped others to ease the transition from life in Puerto Rico to life in Brooklyn. Estepa also offers insight on the differences between "pre-war" and "post-war" Puerto Ricans. He adds that more of an initiative should be taken by Puerto Ricans in New York in 1974; to take advantage of all the educational as well as occupational opportunities that existed within the city in the late-twentieth century. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Denis, Antonia; Estepa, Julio, 1918-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; Race relations |z United States; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Ferrell, Julio, 1973 May 10; 1976.001.017
  Julio Ferrell was born in 1892 in San Juan, Puerto Rico. After training as a carpenter in Puerto Rico, he traveled to Brooklyn aboard the Hellen as a stowaway in 1924. It was there that he primarily worked in factories; beginning with a job at the Brillo Company. He first resided in his brother's apartment on Sands Street, and later moved to a house on Prospect Street, in what is now the DUMBO neighborhood of Brooklyn. At the time of the interview in 1973, Ferrell lived on Union Street in the Carroll Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn
  Julio Ferrell begins the interview by recounting the lives of family members who raised him in Puerto Rico. He shares his experiences as a rebellious young man who, on a whim, left Puerto Rico as stowaway in 1924 and wound up making a new life for himself in Brooklyn. Ferrell recounts the working conditions in Brooklyn's factories and describes his relations with bosses and co-workers of different ethnic backgrounds. He recalls housing conditions and rent prices in the 1920s and 1930s. Ferrell also touches on the subject of racial discrimination; both in Puerto Rico and in New York. Interview in Spanish conducted by Tomás Rivera and Pedro Rivera.